Hello ESL 75 students, welcome to week 6 and the
next set of idioms. this week, we are going to ...
be working on weather and Direction idioms. there are 14.
that means 10 plus 4 more.
I'm going to go over each one in a little
bit more detail, so we can understand them a little ...
better.
Of Course, during class, this upcoming week, I'll also explain
them while in person over Zoom. But I hope this ...
video will be helpful for you.
So we're going to start with our very first weather
idiom. And it is, "clear the air". and when we ...
use the idiom "clear the air", what we're really talking
about is that there is some kind of problem between ...
ourselves, and the person we're speaking with, so maybe we
have had a very uncomfortable situation. there is some kind ...
of problem, and so when we say, "I want to
clear the air." that means, I want to make sure ...
that we talk about this problem, that we're very uncomfortable
about, and hopefully by talking about the problem, we solve ...
the problem. So its like the air is polluted, it's
bad air because the problem is present, and we're not ...
talking about it. so the moment we clear up the
problem, and we find a solution.
It's like saying, that the air we now is clean.
we can breathe more easily. It is no longer uncomfortable ...
because the problem is gone.
Now,
Number two is a kind of person that we sometimes
have in our lives. Now, this is what we call ...
"a fair weather friend"
If the weather is good, this friend is great. So
if everything is great in life, they are your best ...
friend. The moment you have problems, Let's say, it's like
saying the weather is bad, then this friend is no ...
longer your friend. They run away because they don't want
to deal with your problems, so they're only around when ...
everything is good in life. they're not there for you
when you need them, so not a very good friend.
Number three "to be in the dark" means, Well, what
happens when you're in the dark and there's no light?
in this case, it means instead of I can't see
anything, it means, I don't know anything. So, if somebody ...
starts talking to you about a topic where you have
no idea, you can say, "I'm in the dark. I ...
don't know what you're talking about."
Because you have no clue, no idea.
Number 4. When it says, "it's raining cats and dogs."
that means you have very heavy rain. pretend like dogs ...
are falling from the sky, and cats. you can imagine,
that would mean there's a lot of rain falling down ...
at that point, so you might walk outside, and suddenly
it starts raining really really hard. you might say, "Wow!
it's really raining cats and dogs outside." because it's really
falling,  a lot of rain is falling down.
Um,
If you say you're number 5, "on cloud nine" You're
a very happy person. something wonderful has just happened in ...
your life, and you are so happy. And that would
mean, you feel like you're in heaven, and you're on ...
a beautiful fluffy cloud, and it's something we would say
"on cloud nine "you're so happy.
Number 6, "to set somebody straight." Now, this is when
you give somebody advice, but you give it with a ...
warning more like "mm mmm mm." Meaning, you think somebody
is doing something wrong
And You want to help them by telling them, "stop
doing this! this is wrong! this is bad! this will ...
be bad for you!" usually, you can say this to
a family member, your children, good friends. Usually, you wouldn't ...
say this to a stranger. it's for somebody you really
know very well and you
Care About them a lot, so you want them to
do the right thing. you don't want them to make ...
huge mistakes in their life, and in this situation when
you want to "set somebody straight" it means, you think ...
that they have gone down the wrong road in life,
so you want to set them back on the correct ...
path, and so when we say "straight" That means, that's
the correct path, the correct Road in life, and you ...
want to take them from going sideways to going back
straight and ahead. So that's "to set somebody straight."
Remember, only use it with people you really know well.
and care about.
Alright number 7, "to Feel under the weather" Now, when
you're feeling under the weather, you're feeling sick. You're like, ...
"Achoo." and somebody says, "how are you feeling?" and you
say, "Oh today, I'm feeling under the weather. I think ...
I have a fever. I don't feel so good."
That means, "to feel under the weather" you're feeling like,
it's raining. it's bad, and your health is not so ...
good.
Number 8. "any port in the storm" Now, this is
something we talk about when we feel we're in a ...
situation where we don't have many options, many choices. so,
we'll choose whatever is there, whatever option we have open.
so for example, this comes from ships when we used
to travel more by ship. If a ship see the ...
storm on the horizon, they know a storm is coming,
then they don't care as much about where they're going ...
to hide from the storm. they're going to go to
any port, any place that they can to hide from ...
this terrible storm that is coming, and that is the
same thing with us in our lives. a lot of ...
the time if you're in a situation where we don't
have many choices, we will choose whatever choice is the ...
easiest at that very moment because we want to make
sure that we are safe.
Alright,
Going on to number 9. "as the crow flies" yes,
the crow is back again. last time, we talked about ...
"eating crow" and now, we're going to talk more about
how we're going to talk about that same Blackbird again, ...
but this time it's talking not about
Bad things, but it's just talking about, "how do I
get from one place to another the fastest way I ...
can?" so we have to remember, birds can fly. We
unfortunately cannot unless of course we take an airplane. but ...
it is course faster to fly than it is to
walk or drive, so if we say, "I'm going to ...
go the way the crow flies" that really means, "I'm
going to get from one place to another as quickly ...
as possible. to fastest route or this fastest way to
get to my destination." so you're not going to go ...
the long way. you're going to go to the short
way. so you make it there.
quickly.
And That's generally how we use, "as the crow flies"
because then you're choosing the quickest way.
Now, Number 10.
When something is "going south" that means, our situation is
getting worse. So if you say that for example, that ...
your, let me see, that your husband  maybe is
having problems at work, and his boss is giving less ...
and less work. you might say, "oh the situation is
going south" meaning, the situation is getting worse.
And it's usually a very negative kind of idiom.
Number 11, on the other way is when you say
something is full of "blue skies" or somebody is full ...
of ways to see the world in "Blue Skies" it
means, they see things a little too nicely. if you ...
remember, when we did meeting people idioms, and we talked
about somebody "Whistling Dixie" where they see the world in ...
a little too positively, this is the same case, if
somebody thinks of everything as "Blue Skies" where there is ...
no rain, and there is nothing else, then, they see
the world a little too positively. it's not close to ...
reality.
Numbrt 12 is "a bolt from the blue" this means,
something surprising and unexpected has happened in your life. just ...
like seeing lightning come out of blue sky. there shouldn't
be anything, right? and this is something that is actually ...
a natural phenomenon that sometimes does happen when people will
see lightning from miles away, but there is no cloud ...
in the sky. So it's very surprising because usually thunder,
and lightning comes with storms, right? storm clouds, rain. but ...
sometimes, it's very strange, but the weather happens where a
lightning bolt comes from 10 miles away, and there is ...
a cloud, but it's way way over there, and you
say, "how is that possible? It was so surprising."
When you say this in life, you're usually saying that
you witnessed a situation where it was a huge surprise.
you are very surprised that something happened, and so you
might say, "Wow! when my aunt Melda showed up on ...
my doorstep yesterday. it was a bolt from the blue.
I didn't expect her to come to my house. I ...
had no idea she was coming."
And the last one that we have for this week
is, "The Calm before the storm" so, this is usually ...
in a situation where we can
Predict that Something bad is going to happen soon in
the future, so that usually when these situations happen, there's ...
usually...this is once again explaining weather phenomenon,  so usually,
if you're out on the sea or  near the ...
ocean, is usually very nice and calm, the water is
nice. there's a blue sky.
And then A storm comes in very quickly, and things
get bad, right? things get worse.
So when we say, "this was the Calm before the
storm" that means, this is the period of time before, ...
you know, a big problem happens in my life or
a  very bad situation is about to happen. I ...
can see it coming from a from a little distance.
and I know it's going to get worse. so for ...
example, let's say, you made a big mistake at work,
and that point it still hasn't come to your boss, ...
where your boss will find out what's actually happened, so
if your boss finds out, you know at that moment ...
you're in trouble. so before that, you call that, "the
Calm before the storm" you know you can predict
That you will have a big problem coming very soon.
Alright, Well I hope this video helps you a little
bit, understand these idioms about weather and directions a little ...
bit more. we will once again talk about this in
class this week, so I will hopefully see most of ...
you then.
And if Not, you guys can watch the recording from
this week, so...
Thank you so much I hope this helps you.
And take care everyone. Bye.